Jas Sohi

Problem-solving Inventory Management Professional, Seeking Data Analyst Opportunities j450h1@gmail.com

Summary

Problem solving, big picture thinker, and team player with a strong technical background; Jas is a logical thinker who works well with data and who always uses the appropriate technology to aid in decision making. Jas is adaptable and considered by many as a jack of all trades; however, he knows the value of specializing and is now focusing on his passion: Data Science. In January, Jas received his final certificate as part of the Johns Hopkins Data Science Specialization after completing the capstone project in the R and Python programing languages (which is showcased on his website jassohi.com). He is one of the few to complete all courses with distinction (mark > 90%). Never one to stop learning, Jas joined the 1st ever cohort of Udacity's Data Analyst Nanodegree. He will complete 5 interesting projects to showcase his data science skills specifically with R and Python (as well MongoDB, SQL, D3). He went above and beyond in the first 2 projects and he was offered the position of Code Reviewer! Remember, JAS like JAZZ music! https://www.coursera.org/specialization/jhudatascience/1/overview https://www.udacity.com/course/nd00 www.jassohi.com Specialties: Data Analysis, Business Process Improvement, Inventory Management, Forecasting, Web design, Information Systems, Programming, Business Intelligence, R, Python, MongoDB, SQL

Skills & Expertise

Data Analysis

Inventory Management

Business Process Improvement

Customer Service

Microsoft Excel

Business Intelligence

Supply Chain

Leadership

Forecasting

R

Python

SQL

NoSQL

MongoDB

Tableau

XML

Bash

Github

Git

Pandas

Poker

Negotiation

Marketing

Google Analytics

Project Management

Statistics

Teamwork

Pivot Tables

Web Design

Wordpress

Joomla

Logistics

Inside Sales

Google Adwords

Adobe Creative Suite

HTML + CSS

cPanel

Writing

Vlookup

OlikView

Task Management

Machine Learning

Databases

Smartsheet

Highly detail oriented

SQL Server Management Studio

Web Analytics

ERD

Database Design

Experience

Udacity Code Reviewer at Udacity

March 2015 - Present (2 months)

Udacity is a for-profit educational organization based in Mountain View, California and was co-founded by former head of Google X, Sebastian Thrun. Thrun led the development of the Google self-driving car. Udacity is considered "Serious online education for serious people." Being part of Udacity's first ever Data Analyst Nanodegree cohort, I was selected to be one of the very first Udacity Code Reviewers. I review student project submissions and do both a thorough code review as well as a project evaluation. I strive to give actionable and helpful feedback to students while also improving my code reviewing skills at the same time.

Supply Chain Coordinator at BuildDirect

August 2013 - November 2014 (1 year 4 months)

*Ensured the accuracy of ETAs within the inventory system and promptly communicated changes to the Sales team (delays, early containers, etc.) *Lead and trained the new Inventory Administration team of 5 to ensure the analysts could focus on their core competencies: analysis and supplier relationship management. *Lead weekly Inventory Administration meetings and kept team focused on the weekly agenda *Put in place checks & balances to significantly reduce ETA delays (from over 30 to nearly 0) *Quality control/data integrity of over 20 Smartsheets *Designed the Container Tracking Smartsheet to replace inefficient email processes and increase transparency and accountability *Helped lean out Supply Chain processes: Transfers, Returns, Billing, & Container Tracking *Acting as the one of the main contacts for our 4PL Supply Chain partner ABF *Scoped out, tested, and implemented the Freshdesk Ticketing system to organize all warehouse requests into a central system segregated from emails. *Managed the Project Queue as well as worked on several projects to improve/develop processes *Transfers - Saved thousands of dollars in freight by optimizing shipments based on 12 different analysts' requests. Managed an annual budget of a quarter million. *Droptask - Introduced a project management tool to visualize the Project Queue and help prioritize and highlight important projects.

3 recommendations available upon request

Inventory Management Analyst at BuildDirect

May 2012 - August 2013 (1 year 4 months)

Reporting to the Director of Inventory Replenishment, Jason McMurdo; managed inventory for the Engineered Hardwood & Accessories categories representing over a dozen different vendors & over 400 SKU/Locations. Previously, managed the Porcelain & Ceramic category which is one of the Top 9 Categories at BD. Major responsibilities included inventory forecasting, replenishment planning, reconciliation, data analysis, and supplier communication. Keeping out of stocks low and monitoring hundreds of SKUs was a daily challenge. *Founding member who helped establish the new Inventory Department *Introduced Toggl to track daily tasks, visualize, and prioritize the work of the department *Recommendations made to improve the Product Launch Process from a holistic point of view. *Strong work ethic & focus demonstrated on a daily basis - demonstrated ability to work well under pressure and adaptable in a rapidly changing, dynamic environment. *Worked extensively with ABF Freight System's WMS - Logiview and reconciling inventory *Developed Excel-based Inventory Reports to summarizes data for key stakeholders

Inside Sales Rep at BuildDirect

October 2010 - May 2012 (1 year 8 months)

Reporting to the Director of Sales, James Komenda; ensured customer satisfaction by helping customers throughout the entire purchase cycle: order processing, logistics management and order tracking, warranty or damage in transit claims, and general product inquiries. *85% of my customers rated my customer service as either good or excellent. *Finished May 2012 (last month in Sales) with personal best of \$150k in Revenue showing steady progress from the start of the year. *Contributed over \$1.1 million to top line growth in a product category known for low minimum order sizes, lower than average margins, and long lead times

before closing (2011). *Consistently amongst the highest amount of daily touches with potential customers.

- *Recommended several suggestions to help improve business processes and increase efficiency. *Self-starter
- Designed a tile layout diagram to educate customers on correct installation procedures. This helped to reduce customer error when installing product resulting in less claims.

2 recommendations available upon request

Senior Sales Consultant at Bell Mobility

August 2008 - October 2010 (2 years 3 months)

Reporting to the Virgin Mobile store manager; sold the complete solution: handsets, plans, and accessories. Also performed other daily tasks such as opening/closing the kiosk, assisting customers, and activating phones. *100% score on a November mystery shop (2nd out of 9 employees). *Exceeded targets for 9 months and green in all metrics (activations, warranties, and accessories). *\$43,500 added to bottom line with 145 activations in 2009. *As a key holder and senior consultant, helped train newer employees (Amy, Johannes, and Jess). *Strong work ethic demonstrated with 200% to target for postpaid sales in August 2010.

1 recommendation available upon request

Print Distribution Associate (Volunteer) at VANOC

February 2010 - February 2010 (1 month)

Produced, organized, and distributed event results to major broadcasters, such as CBC and NBC, during the 2010 Winter Olympics.

Graphics Technical Specialist (Volunteer) at SFU Business Yearbook

July 2007 - December 2007 (6 months)

Reporting to the editor-in-chief, Griselda Zhou, converted yearbook content into HTML using Adobe Dreamweaver and also provided technical advice as part of the SFU Business Yearbook team.

Census Enumerator at Statistics Canada

July 2006 - August 2006 (2 months)

Reported daily to the crew leader, Sally-Ann Melonari, took a list of addresses/phone numbers and contacted citizens, by phone or directly, urging them to complete their 2006 Census forms.

Education

Udacity

Data Analyst Nanodegree, Data Science, 2014 - 2015

British Columbia Institute of Technology

Data Modeling/Warehousing and Database Administration, 2014 - 2014

Grade: 88%

The Johns Hopkins University

Coursera Specialization, Data Science, 2014 - 2014

Grade: A

Simon Fraser University

BBA, MIS, Finance, and Entrepreneurship, 2004 - 2009

Activities and Societies: BASS Yearbook Team, BLAH weekly intramurals, Finance Club, MIS Club, &

Punjabi Student Association

Certifications

Data Science Specialization

Coursera Verified Certificates License 7RdAH4nkEe December 2014

Intro to Data Science

Udacity January 2015

Data Wrangling with MongoDB

Udacity February 2015

Certified Supply Chain Professional

APICS August 2013

Practical Machine Learning

Coursera Verified Certificates License M6M5CUAMZD September 2014

Developing Data Products

Coursera Verified Certificates License TL2EVX24B7 September 2014

Regression Models

Coursera Verified Certificates License CSRBQYL3XX September 2014

Statistical Inference

Coursera Verified Certificates License 2NKUAQ2CGT August 2014

Reproducible Research

Coursera Verified Certificates License FB9GXTN7ZZ August 2014

Exploratory Data Analysis

Coursera Verified Certificates License M57JCYPMNH July 2014

Getting and Cleaning Data

Coursera Verified Certificates License L25L7X7CN5 July 2014

R Programming

Coursera Verified Certificates License UXJV7UT6M5 June 2014

The Data Scientist's Toolbox

Coursera Verified Certificates License X8VCKHNV3X May 2014

Data Analysis and Statistical Inference

Coursera Verified Certificates License C75PZX49F7 April 2014

try-sql

Code School

Data Analysis with R

Udacity April 2015

Intro to Machine Learning

Udacity April 2015

Courses

BBA, MIS, Finance, and Entrepreneurship

Simon Fraser University

Data and Decisions I BUEC 232

Introduction to Computers and Information Systems in BUS 237

Business

Information Analysis and Systems Design
Event Driven Programming - Visual Basic
CMPT 110
Project Management
BUS 361
New Venture Planning
BUS 477
Management Support Systems
BUS 462
Managing Data Communications
BUS 492

Data Modeling/Warehousing and Database Administration

British Columbia Institute of Technology

Relational Database Design and SQL CMPT 1630

Data Analyst Nanodegree, Data Science

Udacity

MongoDB for Python Developers M101P: MongoDB University

Independent Coursework

Digital Analytics Fundamentals Analytics Academy

Google Analytics Platform Principles Analytics Academy

Languages

English

French
Punjabi
(Native or bilingual proficiency)
Hindi
(Native or bilingual proficiency)
Urdu
(Native or bilingual proficiency)

Honors and Awards

Outperformed S&P 500 in Investors of Tomorrow Stock Market Competition (2008) Vancouver Sun Run 2011 Time 1:16 Vancouver Sun Run 2012 Time: 1:09 Vancouver Sun Run 2013 Time: 57:58 Grouse Grind June 2013 53:00 Tough Mudder - Whistler 2013 Finisher - with a dislocated shoulder:) SeaWheeze Half Marathon - 2:31 2014 BuildDirect Charity Poker Champion

Interests

Skiing, Ball Hockey, Rollerblading, Working Out, Basketball, UFC, Video Games, Computers, Hockey, Electronics, Bollywood, Motorcycles, Hiking, Comedy Shows, Gadgets, Podcasts, Mobile Phones, Financial News, Running, Xbox, Red Bull, Diet Coke, Floatation Tanks

Test Scores

CMPT 1630 - Midterm

June 2014 Score: 91.58%

This exam was based heavily upon understanding database modelling concepts as opposed to just SQL coding.

Projects

Python - Codeacademy

September 2014 to Present

Members:Jas Sohi

Completed an intense Python course that involved developing a simple Battleship® game from scratch.

Data Science Capstone - Predictive Text Model

December 2014 to Present

Members:Jas Sohi

John Hopkins partnered with SwitKey on this capstone project for the Data Science specialization through Coursera. After completing 9 Data Science courses over a 9 month period, participants took a corpus of text from twitter, news sites, and blogs and used it to train a predictive text model. I used Python to build the n-grams and R to build the web app itself through the Shiny framework. Check out the web app to see it in action for yourself!

Udacity Data Analyst Nanodegree - Project 1: Analyzing the NYC Subway Dataset

January 2015 to Present

Members:Jas Sohi

This is the first project for the Udacity Data Analyst - Nanodegree. The ultimate goal of the analysis is to see whether NYC subway ridership is higher on rainy days vs non-rainy days. Python (NumPy, Pandas, ggplot) and Tableau were used for the analysis and visualizations respectively.

Udacity Data Analyst Nanodegree - Project 2: Data Wrangling with MongoDB

February 2015 to Present

Members:Jas Sohi

This is the second project for the Udacity Data Analyst - Nanodegree. I was tasked at choosing any area of the world from https://www.openstreetmap.org and used data munging techniques, such as assessing the quality of the data for validity, accuracy, completeness, consistency and uniformity, to clean the OpenStreetMap data. I chose the GVRD, or Greater Vancouver Regional District, which is my home region. Python was used to clean the data and prepare it for inserting into the NoSQL database: MongoDB. Many

queries were then run to arrive at interesting findings. Finally, an R Markdown document was created to easily showcase all the queries in the final pdf report.

Volunteer Experience

Great Canadian Shoreline Cleanup at SFU Alumni

June 2013 - June 2014 (1 year 1 month)

Jas Sohi

Problem-solving Inventory Management Professional, Seeking Data Analyst Opportunities j450h1@gmail.com



6 people have recommended Jas

"Jas Sohi was a pleasure to work with, he is thoughtful, engaging and consummate team player. Jas was instrumental in the evolution of the inventory replenishment department at BuildDirect. He developed processes that focused on adding value and removing waste. He was willing to continually go above and beyond to accomplish any task or project that was assigned. A few highlights of his time at BuildDirect are as follows: 1 - Improved a lot of inefficient and manual processes to reduce redundant work such as the Container Tracking smartsheet 2 - Managed the smartsheet implementation and created dozens of smartsheets and reports to support optimized processes 3 - Tested, implemented and oversaw the fresh desk ticketing system 4 - Standardized and implemented jargon such as WETA and SETA so all departments spoke the same language "

— Jason McMurdo, CPC, managed Jas

"Jas is detailed and process oriented person, with in-depth knowledge of Supply Chain and Inventory Management. He is passionate about his work and always get things done. Working with Jas has been a pleasure and easy task, bringing his A game every time. He has helped Inventory team @ BuildDirect gaining significant data, process improvement, overall reaching great results and becoming one of the best teams in the company. His training and leadership was always innovative and inspiring."

— Mack Raicevic, worked directly with Jas

"Jas is the consummate professional who knows how to drive operational improvements with passion, intelligence and clear communication. Jas and I worked well together at BuildDirect building the inventory department and developing new processes for the company. His proven track record of successful projects was made possible by his broad knowledge and cross functional expertise within operations, sales and marketing, make Jas a pro-active contributor, any organization would be fortunate to have as part of their team. I can highly recommend Jas for a variety of operations, logistics and IT positions."

— **Jim Hourigan**, managed Jas indirectly

"Jas placed and managed a large order for me. He did a great job helping me get the order on time as I had various contraints with contractors. Subsequently I needed to place a further order and Jas recognized

me, quickly assessed my needs and was creative in helping address them. In addition to being reliable and creative, Jas is also very personable. It was a pleasure working with him."

— Suresh Bhatia, was Jas's client

"Jas Sohi has been one of the most intelligent and reliable Sales Representatives in the BuildDirect sales team. He is a consummate professional who consistently receives excellent feedback from clients due to his ability to manage their expectations and communicate with them effectively regarding their sales orders. One of the key things that impresses me about Jas is that he is still able to generate over a million dollars of revenue to date for his product lines that are known for having lower margins and longer lead times, a feat that is considered challenging for a Sales Representative in his position. He also demonstrates excellent time-management skills while providing great customer service, evident from the high volume of clients he interacts with on a daily basis. Furthermore, his passion for technology is apparent through proposing ideas to improve business processes and maximize productivity for the company. He is considered an "A" player at BuildDirect, and I firmly believe he is one of the most productive Sales Representatives in the team."

— Rodney Noriega, Sales, Business Development, BuildDirect, worked directly with Jas at BuildDirect

"I am proud to say that I have worked with Jas during my time as a sales consultant at Bell Mobility. Jas is a very focused worker that ensures that all things that needs to be "done" gets done. He is a person you can rely on for specific and measurable information. I look forward to seeing his success in the future."

— **Keith Wong**, Senior Sales Consultant, Bell Mobility, worked directly with Jas at Bell Mobility

Contact Jas on LinkedIn